<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Maxime Garcia</title>
    <link>http://typhomnt.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Maxime Garcia</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 16:29:59 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://typhomnt.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Animation Target Constraint</title>
      <link>http://typhomnt.github.io/animation_target_ctr/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 16:22:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://typhomnt.github.io/animation_target_ctr/</guid>
      <description> As-rigid-as-possible target constraint </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Animation Transfer</title>
      <link>http://typhomnt.github.io/animation_transfer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 16:22:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://typhomnt.github.io/animation_transfer/</guid>
      <description>One main goal of my thesis is to find a way to animate 3D characters using physical props as an animation tool. The motivation is to create an animation sequence from a play with figurines, trying to reproduce what the player was imagining.
Space Time Doodle Transfer examples Below, I show transfered space-time doodles into animation sequences. It is important to note that all actions were learnt for the two first examples as well as for the garden example.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Animation Transfer for two characters: Part 1</title>
      <link>http://typhomnt.github.io/animation_transfer_two_chars/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 16:22:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://typhomnt.github.io/animation_transfer_two_chars/</guid>
      <description>function passWord() { var testV = 1; var pass1 = prompt(&#39;Protected Page, Please Enter The Password&#39;,&#39; &#39;); while (testV passWord()  In the animation transfer article, I presented a method to create a animation sequence from a 6D trajectory. This method is centered around one character at a time. Here, I propose a way to extend it in order to take into account multiple characters and their interactions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Art Ressource</title>
      <link>http://typhomnt.github.io/3d_art/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 16:22:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://typhomnt.github.io/3d_art/</guid>
      <description> The Band of the Hawk by typhomnt on Sketchfab   SkyEngine Bob by typhomnt on Sketchfab   Phantasy Star Online 2 Ray Partizan by typhomnt on Sketchfab   Soul Calibur Fan Art First Attempt by typhomnt on Sketchfab   Soul Edge Fan art First Attempt by typhomnt on Sketchfab  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Art Ressource</title>
      <link>http://typhomnt.github.io/art/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 16:22:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://typhomnt.github.io/art/</guid>
      <description>3D art Music</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Art Ressource</title>
      <link>http://typhomnt.github.io/music/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 16:22:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://typhomnt.github.io/music/</guid>
      <description>Here are some of my piano recordings.
Chopin Etude 5 Op 25 &amp;ldquo;Wrong Notes&amp;rdquo; (Recorded in 2015)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Base Mesh Creation</title>
      <link>http://typhomnt.github.io/bmesh/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 16:22:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://typhomnt.github.io/bmesh/</guid>
      <description>This project is in fact a second attemp to implement a fast base mesh creation method from this paper. The main idea is to create a animable mesh from a skeleton whose joints are represented by spheres with variable radius defining the distance from the mesh vertices. This mesh generation algorithm is decomposed into 3 steps: First a simple init mesh is computed connecting each joint with successive quad extrusion and convex hull computation for T-junctions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Basic Toon Shading</title>
      <link>http://typhomnt.github.io/basic_toon_shading/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 16:22:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://typhomnt.github.io/basic_toon_shading/</guid>
      <description>Toon Shading in animation Here is an example of toon shading during an uppercut jab animation downsampled at 15 fps</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bloom Effect</title>
      <link>http://typhomnt.github.io/bloom_effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 16:22:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://typhomnt.github.io/bloom_effect/</guid>
      <description>Bloom effect Here is an example of Bloom post process effect</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functionnal Programming Resources</title>
      <link>http://typhomnt.github.io/functionnal_programming_practs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 16:22:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://typhomnt.github.io/functionnal_programming_practs/</guid>
      <description>This course is proposed to DLST computer science Licence 1 students and presents an introduction to Functionnal Programming in OCaml.
Practicals Fractals
Fractals Solution
Optional Project</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laban Effort Animation Transfer</title>
      <link>http://typhomnt.github.io/laban_transfer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 16:22:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://typhomnt.github.io/laban_transfer/</guid>
      <description>One important aspect of my thesis work is adding expressivity to an input &amp;ldquo;neutral&amp;rdquo; animation. In our work, we decided to take the Laban Effort space as the main representation of the expressivity. This 4D space is divided into Space, Time, Weight and Flow axis. The Space axis describes how direct or indirect a movment is, Time describes if a movment is rather sudden or sustained while Weight differenciate Light from Strong motions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Portfolio Enseignement Label RES</title>
      <link>http://typhomnt.github.io/teaching_portfolio/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 16:22:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://typhomnt.github.io/teaching_portfolio/</guid>
      <description>function passWord() { var testV = 1; var pass1 = prompt(&#39;Protected Page, Please Enter The Password&#39;,&#39; &#39;); while (testV passWord()  Concevoir des enseignements qui favorisent l&amp;rsquo;apprentissage de chacun Objectif De Janvier à Mai 2017 (de même en 2018), j&amp;rsquo;ai enseigné la programmation fonctionnelle en Licence 1. Je me suis donné pour objectif de proposer un enseignement adapté à chacun de mes élèves, permettant aux plus à l&amp;rsquo;aise d’aller plus loin tout en apportant un soutien à ceux qui étaient le plus en difficulté.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ray Tracing Resources</title>
      <link>http://typhomnt.github.io/raytracing_practs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 16:22:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://typhomnt.github.io/raytracing_practs/</guid>
      <description>This course is proposed to MSIAM M1 students and presents an introduction to Ray casting, Ray tracing, Ray Marching and Physically Based Rendering methods. I would like to thank Romain Vergne for his course slides and the two first practicals.
Course Slides Ray Casting
Ray Tracing/Ray Marching
Physically Based Rendering
Practicals Base Code
Ray Casting
Ray Tracing
Physically Based Rendering
Ray Marching</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research Work</title>
      <link>http://typhomnt.github.io/research_work/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 16:22:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://typhomnt.github.io/research_work/</guid>
      <description>My main interest of research is to find an intuitive way of animating characters. During my thesis untitled &amp;ldquo;Performence Transfer: Animating Characters by Playing and Acting&amp;rdquo;, I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to find a method for creating expressive character animation sequences using 6D trajectories which contain position and orientation data of a physical prop trajectory (such as HTC Vive controllers). This work tackle three problems: Creating an animation sequence using one 6D trajectory, recognizing and transfering motion qualties and create multi character animations in a storytelling context.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SkyEngine</title>
      <link>http://typhomnt.github.io/skyengine/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 16:22:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://typhomnt.github.io/skyengine/</guid>
      <description>SkyEngine is yet another game engine I am working on together with co-workers and former collegues. The main goal of this engine is to implement recent research work, to make video game and animated movie content easier to create. I would like to thank Julien Daval, Guillaume Cordonnier, Valentin Touzeau, Pierre Casati and Remi Galan Alfonso for contributing to this framework.
Basic Toon Shading | Animation Target Ctr| Bloom Effect</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching Resources</title>
      <link>http://typhomnt.github.io/teaching_ressources/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 16:22:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://typhomnt.github.io/teaching_ressources/</guid>
      <description>Raytracing Ressources
Functionnal Programming
Label RES Portfolio</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>